# **Howard Abbey**

+1 (586) 298-2472

hrabbey@gmail.com

https://www.linkedin.com/in/hrabbey

#### **SUMMARY**

Technical communication and international interface skills proven through over 16 years in the automotive navigation software industry. Attention to detail and ability to gain insight into customer desires resulting in end product enhancement and long-term partnerships.

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

AW Technical Center USA

Assistant Manager, Advanced Engineering

2012 - 2019

- Co-develop proof of concepts, rapid prototypes, and future specifications for Toyota in-dash navigation systems with Japanese, European and local team members.
- Individually represent company at conferences, prospective supplier meetings and in long-term partnerships.
- Present production units, prototypes, future options and innovations internally to company directors, current and prospective customers at conferences, exhibitions, and on-site meetings.
- Supervise 3 Advanced Engineering and Product Planning members, focused on navigation, geospatial, ADAS and autonomous vehicle market research and product innovations for Japanese headquarters.
- Serve as Scrum Master for international research team of 9, supporting rapid prototype screen-flow and proof
  of concept development for next generation ideas
- Contributed to architecture design reviews for improved road traffic detection systems using vehicle GPS probe big data inputs to machine learning models.
- Evaluate and consider metrics to evaluate map (HERE, TomTom, OpenStreetMap), traffic, places/POI and other location based service data providers.

AW Technical Center USA

Program Management Senior Engineer

2005 - 2011

- Retain OEM and Tier 1 (GM and Delphi) partnership and foster desire to continue working together.
- Negotiate and maintain project schedules including deliverables, requirements, and responsibilities.
- Coach coworkers on how best to influence customers and partners to achieve best technical decisions.
- Convey customer desires by authoring requirements in an understandable way for development team.
- Specify electronic and software interfaces between navigation module and vehicle infotainment radio.
- Improve manufacturability and testability while defining new end-user customer focused features.

AW Technical Center USA

Systems Applications Engineer

2002 - 2004

- Coordinate product development and communication as resident engineer and on-site liaison between Delphi and Aisin AW Japan by leading progress and issue tracking meetings.
- Integrate first release hardware of AW navigation module into audio and display components.
- Investigate and debug customer field complaints, manufacturing problems and specification clarification requests.

#### **EDUCATION**

Michigan Technological University

Bachelor of Science, Electrical Engineering dept., Computer Engineering

## LANGUAGE SKILLS

- Fluent English, with ability to convey technical topics to novices.
- Elementary speaking and reading of Japanese